{
  "readings": [
    {
      "reading_title": "The MIT factor: celebrating 150 years of maverick genius",
      "reading_content": "The musician Yo-Yo Ma’s cello may not be the obvious starting point for a journey into one of the world’s great universities. But, as you quickly realise when you step inside the Massachusetts Institute of Technology, there’s precious little going on that you would normally see on a university campus. The cello, resting in a corner of MIT’s celebrated media laboratory – a hub of creativity – looks like any other electric classical instrument. But it is much more. Machover, the composer, teacher and inventor responsible for its creation, calls it a ‘hyperinstrument’,  a sort of thinking machine that allows  Ma and his cello to interact with one another and make music together. ‘The aim is to build an instrument worthy of a great musician like Yo-Yo Ma that can understand what he is trying to do and respond to it,’ Machover says. The cello has numerous sensors across its body and by measuring the pressure, speed and angle of the virtuoso’s performance it can interpret his mood and engage with it, producing extraordinary new sounds. The virtuoso cellist frequently performs on the instrument as he tours around the world. \nMachover’s passion for pushing at the boundaries of the existing world to extend and unleash human potential is not a bad description of MIT as a whole. This unusual community brings highly gifted, highly motivated individuals together from a vast range of disciplines, united by a common desire: to leap into the dark and reach for the unknown.\nThe result of that single unifying ambition is visible all around. For the past 150 years, MIT has been leading the world into the future. The discoveries of its teachers and students have become the common everyday objects that we now all take for granted. The telephone, electromagnets, radars, high-speed photography,  office photocopiers, cancer treatments,  pocket calculators,  computers,  the Internet, the decoding of the human genome, lasers, space travel … the list of innovations that involved essential contributions from MIT and its faculty goes on and on.\nFrom the moment MIT was founded by William Barton Rogers in 1861, it was clear what it was not. While Harvard stuck to the English model of a classical education, with its emphasis on Latin and Greek, MIT looked to the German system of learning based on research and hands-on experimentation. Knowledge was at a premium, but it had to be useful.\nThis down-to-earth quality is enshrined in the school motto,  Mens et manus – Mind and hand – as well as its logo, which shows a gowned scholar standing beside an ironmonger bearing a hammer and anvil.  That symbiosis of intellect and craftsmanship still suffuses the institute’s classrooms, where students are not so much taught as engaged and inspired.\nTake  Christopher  Merrill,  21,  a  third-year undergraduate in computer science. He is spending most of his time on a competition set in his robotics class. The contest is to see which student can most effectively program a robot to build a  house out of blocks in under ten minutes.  Merrill says he could have gone for the easiest route – designing a simple robot that would build the house quickly.  But he wanted to try to master an area of robotics that remains unconquered – adaptability, the ability of the robot to rethink its plans as the environment around it changes, as would a human. ‘I like to take on things that have never been done before rather than to work in an iterative way just making small steps forward,’ he explains.\nMerrill is already planning the start-up he wants to set up when he graduates in a year’s time. He has an idea for an original version of a contact lens that would augment reality by allowing consumers to see additional visual information. He is fearful that he might be just too late in taking his concept to market, as he has heard that a Silicon Valley firm is already developing something similar. As such, he might become one of many MIT graduates who go on to form companies that fail. Alternatively, he might become one of those who go on to succeed in spectacular fashion. And there are many of them. A survey of living MIT alumni found that they have formed 25,800 companies, employing more than three million people, including about a quarter of the workforce of Silicon Valley.\nWhat MIT delights in is taking brilliant minds from around the world in vastly diverse disciplines and putting them together. You can see that in its sparkling new David Koch Institute for Integrative Cancer Research, which brings scientists, engineers and clinicians under one roof. Or in its Energy Initiative, which acts as a bridge for MIT’s combined work across all its five schools, channelling huge resources into the search for a solution to global warming. It works to improve the efficiency of existing energy sources, including nuclear power. It is also forging ahead with alternative energies from solar to wind and geothermal, and has recently developed the use of viruses to synthesise batteries that could prove crucial in the advancement of electric cars.\nIn the words of Tim Berners-Lee, the Briton who invented the World Wide Web, ‘It’s not just another university. Even though I spend my time with my head buried in the details of web technology, the nice thing is that when I do walk the corridors, I bump into people who are working in other fields with their students that are fascinating, and that keeps me intellectually alive.",
      "question_count": 2,
      "true_false_question": {
        "title": "Read the passage and decide whether each question is TRUE, FALSE or NOT GIVEN",
        "priority": 1,
        "questions": [
          {
            "question": "The activities going on at the MIT campus are like those at any other university.",
            "answer": "FALSE",
            "answer_description": "(... there's precious little going on that you would normally see on a university campus.)"
          },
          {
            "question": "Harvard and MIT shared a similar approach to education when they were founded.",
            "answer": "FALSE",
            "answer_description": "(While Harvard stuck to the English model of a classical education, with its emphasis on Latin and Greek, MIT looked to the German system of learning based on research and hands-on experimentation.)"
          },
          {
            "question": "The school motto was suggested by a former MIT student.",
            "answer": "NOT GIVEN",
            "answer_description": "(The motto is mentioned, but we are not told who suggested it.)"
          },
          {
            "question": "MIT’s logo reflects the belief that intellect and craftsmanship go together.",
            "answer": "TRUE",
            "answer_description": "(... its logo, which shows a gowned scholar standing beside an ironmonger bearing a hammer and anvil. That symbiosis of intellect and craftsmanship ...)"
          },
          {
            "question": "Silicon Valley companies pay higher salaries to graduates from MIT.",
            "answer": "NOT GIVEN",
            "answer_description": "(There is nothing in the text about how much MIT graduates are paid in Silicon Valley.)"
          }
        ]
      },
      "gap_question": {
        "title": "Read Questions and quickly check what information you need for each gap. Then, using the title to find the right part of the passage, answer the questions.\nChoose NO MORE THAN TWO WORDS from the passage for each answer.\n\nChristopher Merrill – student at MIT",
        "priority": 2,
        "questions": [
          {
            "question": "Degree subject: $...$",
            "answers": [
              {
                "answer": [
                  "computer science"
                ]
              }
            ]
          },
          {
            "question": "Competition:  to $...$ the automated construction of a house ",
            "answers": [
              {
                "answer": [
                  "program"
                ]
              }
            ]
          },
          {
            "question": "Special focus on:  the $...$ of robots",
            "answers": [
              {
                "answer": [
                  "adaptability"
                ]
              }
            ]
          },
          {
            "question": "Future plans:  to develop new type of $...$",
            "answers": [
              {
                "answer": [
                  "contact lens"
                ]
              }
            ]
          }
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "reading_title": "Learning color words",
      "reading_content": "In the course of the first few years of their lives, children who are brought up in English-speaking homes successfully master the use of hundreds of words. Words for objects, actions, emotions and many other aspects of the physical world quickly become part of their infant repertoire. For some reason, however, when it comes to learning color words, the same children perform very badly. At the age of four months, babies can distinguish between basic color categories. Yet it turns out they do this in much the same way as blind children. “Blue” and “yellow” appear in older children’s expressive language in answer to questions such as “What color is this?”, but their mapping of objects to individual colors is haphazard and interchangeable. If shown a blue cup and asked about its color, typical two-year-olds seem as likely to come up with “red” as “blue.” Even after hundreds of training trials, children as old as four may still end up being unable to accurately sort objects by color.\n\nIn an effort to work out why this is, cognitive scientists at Stanford University in California hypothesized that children’s incompetence at color-word learning may be directly linked to the way these words are used in English. While word order for color adjectives varies, they are used overwhelmingly in pre-nominal position (e.g. “blue cup”); in other words, the adjective comes before the noun it is describing. This is in contrast to post-nominal position (e.g. “The cup is blue”) where the adjective comes after the noun. It seems that the difficulty children have may not be caused by any unique property of color, or indeed, of the world. Rather, it may simply come down to the challenge of having to make predictions from color words to the objects they refer to, instead of being able to make predictions from the world of objects to the color words.\nTo illustrate, the word “chair” has a meaning that applies to the somewhat varied set of entities in the world that people use for sitting on. Chairs have features, such as arms and legs and backs, that are combined to some degree in a systematic way; they turn up in a range of chairs of different shapes, sizes, and ages. It could be said that children learn to narrow down the set of cues that make up a chair and in this way they learn the concept associated with that word. On the other hand, color words tend to. be unique and not bound to other specific co-occurring features; there is nothing systematic about color words to help cue their meaning. In the speech that adults direct at children, color adjectives occur pre-nominally (“blue cup”) around 70 percent of the time. This suggests that most of what children hear from adults will, in fact, be unhelpful in learning what color words refer to.\n\nTo explore this idea further, the research team recruited 41 English children aged between 23 and 29 months and carried out a three-phase experiment. It consisted of a pre-test, followed by training in the use of color words, and finally a post-test that was identical to the pre-test. The pre- and post-test materials comprised six objects that were novel to the children. There were three examples of each object in each of three colors—red, yellow, and blue. The objects were presented on trays, and in both tests, the children were asked to pick out objects in response to requests in which the color word was either a prenominal (“Which is the red one?”) or a post-nominal (“Which one is red?”).\nIn the training, the children were introduced to a “magic bucket” containing five sets of items familiar to 26-month-olds (balls, cups, crayons, glasses, and toy bears) in each of the (20) Unit 2 three colors. The training was set up so that half the children were presented with the items one by one and heard them labelled with color words used pre-nominally (“This is a red crayon”), while the other half were introduced to the same items described with a post-nominal color word (“This crayon is red”). After the training, the children repeated the selection task on the unknown items in the post-test. To assess the quality of children’s understanding of the color words, and the effect of each type of training, correct choices on items that were consistent across the pre- and post-tests were used to measure children’s color knowledge.\n\nIndividual analysis of pre- and post-test data, which confirmed parental vocabulary reports, showed the children had at least some knowledge of the three colour words: they averaged two out of three correct choices in response to both pre- and post-nominal question types, which, it has been pointed out, is better than chance. When children’s responses to the question types were assessed independently, performance was at its most consistent when children were both trained and tested on post-nominal adjectives, and worst when trained on pre-nominal adjectives and tested on post-nominal adjectives. Only children who had been trained with post-nominal color-word presentation and then tested with post-nominal question types were significantly more accurate than chance. Comparing the pre- and post-test scores across each condition revealed a significant decline in performance when children were both pre- and post-tested with questions that placed the color words pre-nominally.\nAs predicted, when children are exposed to color adjectives in post-nominal position, they learn them rapidly (after just five training trials per color); when they are presented with them pre-nominally, as English overwhelmingly tends to do, children show no signs of learning.",
      "reading_voice_url": "https://ali-you.github.io/IELTS/reading/level5/voice/lesson2.mp3",
      "question_count": 2,
      "gap_question": {
        "title": "Complete the summary below.\nChoose NO MORE THAN TWO WORDS from the passage for each answer.\n\nThe Hypothesis",
        "priority": 1,
        "questions": [
          {
            "question": "Children learn many words quite quickly, but their ability to learn colour words takes longer than expected. In fact, despite $...$ .",
            "answers": [
              {
                "answer": [
                  "training trials"
                ],
                "answer_description": "Even after hundreds of training trials, children as old as four may still end up being unable ta accurately sort objects by color."
              }
            ]
          },
          {
            "question": "many four-year-olds still struggle to arrange objects into colour categories. Scientists have hypothesised that this is due to the $...$ of the adjectives in a phrase or sentence and the challenges this presents.",
            "answers": [
              {
                "answer": [
                  "position",
                  "pre-nominal position"
                ],
                "answer_description": "In the speech thar adults direct at children, color adjectives occur pre-nominally (“blue cup”) around 70 percent of the time. This suggests that most of what children hear from adults will, in fact, be unhelpful in learning what color words refer to."
              }
            ]
          },
          {
            "question": "While objects consist of a number of $...$ that can be used to recognise other similar objects,",
            "answers": [
              {
                "answer": [
                  "features",
                  "cues"
                ],
                "answer_description": "Chairs have features, such as arms and legs and backs, that are combined to some degree in a systematic way; they turn up in a range of chairs of different shapes, sizes, and ages. It could be said that children learn to narrow down the set of cues that make up a chair..."
              }
            ]
          },
          {
            "question": "the $...$ of a colour cannot be developed using the same approach.",
            "answers": [
              {
                "answer": [
                  "meaning",
                  "concept"
                ],
                "answer_description": "... in this way they learn the concept associated with that word ... there is nothing systematic about color words to help cue their meaning."
              }
            ]
          },
          {
            "question": "As a consequence, the way colour words tend to be used in English may be $...$ to children.",
            "answers": [
              {
                "answer": [
                  "unhelpful"
                ],
                "answer_description": "In the speech that adults direct at children, color adjectives occur pre-nominally (“blue cup”) around 70 percent of the time. This Suggests that most of what children hear from adults will, in fact, be unhelpful in learning what color words refer to."
              }
            ]
          }
        ]
      },
      "multi_choice_question": {
        "title": "Choose TWO letter, A-E",
        "priority": 2,
        "questions": [
          {
            "question": "Which TWO of the following statements about the experiment are true?",
            "selection_count": 2,
            "choices": [
              "The children were unfamiliar with the objects used in the pre- and post-test.",
              "The children had to place the pre- and post-test objects onto coloured trays.",
              "The training was conducted by dividing the children into two groups.",
              "Pre-nominal questions were used less frequently than post-nominal questions in the training.",
              "The researchers were looking for inconsistencies in children's knowledge of word order."
            ],
            "answers": [
              {
                "answer": "A",
                "description": "The pre- and post-test materials comprised six objects that were novel to the children."
              },
              {
                "answer": "C",
                "description": "... half the children were presented with the items one by one and heard them labelled with color words used pre-nominally (“This is a red crayon”), while the other half were introduced to the same items described with a post-nominal color word (“This crayon ts red”)."
              }
            ]
          },
          {
            "question": "Which TWO of the following outcomes are reported in the passage?",
            "selection_count": 2,
            "choices": [
              "Average results contradicted parental assessment of children’s knowledge.",
              "Children who were post-tested using post-nominal adjectives performed well, regardless of the type of training.",
              "Greatest levels of improvement were achieved by children who were trained and post-tested using post-nominal adjectives.",
              "Some children performed less well in the post-test than in the pre-test.",
              "Some children were unable to accurately name any of the colours in the pre- and post-tests."
            ],
            "answers": [
              {
                "answer": "C",
                "description": "Only children who had been trained with post- nominal color-word presentation and then tested with Post-nominal question types were significantly more accurate than chance."
              },
              {
                "answer": "D",
                "description": "Comparing the pre- and post-test scores across each condition revealed a significant decline in performance when children were both pre- and post- tested with questions that placed the color words pre-nominally."
              }
            ]
          }
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "reading_title": "Examining the placebo effect",
      "reading_content": "The fact that taking a fake drug can powerfully improve some people's health—the so-called placebo effect—was long considered an embarrassment to the serious practice of pharmacology, but now things have changed.\n\nSeveral years ago, Merck, a global pharmaceutical company, was falling behind its rivals in sales. To make matters worse, patents on five blockbuster drugs were about to expire, which would allow cheaper generic products to flood the market. In interviews with the press, Edward Scolnick, Merck's Research Director, presented his plan to restore the firm to pre-eminence. Key to his strategy was expanding the company’s reach into the anti-depressant market, where Merck had trailed behind, while competitors like Pfizer and GlaxoSmithKline had created some of the best-selling drugs in the world. “To remain dominant in the future,” he told one media company, “we need to dominate the central nervous system.”\nHis plan hinged on the success of an experimental anti-depressant codenamed MK-869. Still in clinical trials, it was a new kind of medication that exploited brain chemistry in innovative ways to promote feelings of well-being. The drug tested extremely well early on, with minimal side effects. Behind the scenes, however, MK-869 was starting to unravel. TRUE, many test subjects treated with the medication felt their hopelessness and anxiety lift, But so did nearly the same number who took a placebo, a look-alike pill made of milk sugar or another inert substance given to groups of volunteers in subsequent clinical trials to gauge the effectiveness of the real drug by comparison. Ultimately, Merck's venture into the anti-depressant market failed, In the jargon of the industry, the trials crossed the “futility boundary’.\nMK-869 has not been the only much-awaited medical breakthrough to be undone in recent years by the placebo effect. And it’s not only trials of new drugs that are crossing the futility boundary. Some products that have been on the market for decades are faltering in more recent follow-up tests. It’s not that the old medications are getting weaker, drug developers say, It's as if the placebo effect is somehow getting stronger. The fact that an increasing number of medications are unable to beat sugar pills has thrown the industry into crisis. The stakes could hardly be higher To win FDA approval, a new medication must beat placebo in at least two authenticated trials, In today's economy, the fate of a well-established company can hang on the outcome of a handful of tests.\nWhy are fake pills suddenly overwhelming promising new drugs and established medicines alike? The reasons are only just beginning to be understood. A network of independent researchers is doggedly uncovering the inner workings and potential applications of the placebo effect.\nA psychiatrist, William Potter, who knew that some patients really do seem to get healthier for reasons that. have more to do with a doctor's empathy than with the contents of a pill, was baffled by the fact that drugs he had been prescribing for years seemed to be struggling to prove their effectiveness. Thinking that a crucial factor may have been overlooked, Potter combed through his company's database of published and unpublished trials—including those that had been kept secret because of high placebo response. His team aggregated the findings from decades of anti-depressant trials, looking for patterns and trying to see what was changing over time. What they found challenged some of the industry's basic assumptions about its drug-vetting process.\nAssumption number one was that if a trial were managed correctly, a medication would perform as well or badly in a Phoenix hospital as in a Bangalore clinic, Potter discovered, however, that geographic location alone could determine the outcome. By the late 1990s, for example, the anti-anxiety drug Diazepam was still beating placebo in France and Belgium. But when the drug was tested in the U.S., it was likely to fail. Conversely, a similar drug, Prozac, performed better in America than it did in western Europe and South Africa. It was an unsettling prospect: FDA approval could hinge on where the company chose to conduct a trial.\nMistaken assumption number two was that the standard tests used to gauge volunteers’ improvement in trials yielded consistent results, Potter and his colleagues discovered that ratings by trial observers varied significantly from one testing site to another. It was like finding out that the judges in a tight race each had a different idea about the placement of the finish line.\nAfter some coercion by Potter and others, the National Institute of Health (NIH) focused on the issue in 2000, hosting a three-day conference in Washington, and this conference launched a new wave of placebo research in academic laboratories in the U.S. and Italy that would make significant progress toward solving the mystery of what was happening in clinical trials.\nIn one study last year, Harvard Medical School researcher Ted Kaptchuk devised a clever strategy for testing his volunteers’ response to varying levels of therapeutic ritual. The study focused on a common but painful medical condition that costs more than $40 billion a year worldwide to treat. First, the volunteers were placed Tandomly in one of three groups. One group was simply put on a waiting list; researchers know that some patients get better just because they sign up for a trial. Another group received placebo treatment from a clinician who declined to engage in small talk. Volunteers in the third group got the same fake treatment from a clinician who asked them questions about symptoms, outlined the causes of the illness, and displayed optimism about their condition.\nNot surprisingly, the health of those in the third group improved most. In fact, just by participating in the trial, volunteers in this high-interaction group got as much relief ‘as did people taking the two leading prescription drugs for the condition. And the benefits of their “bogus” treatment persisted for weeks afterward, contrary to the belief—widespread in the pharmaceutical industry—that the placebo response is short-lived.\nStudies like this open the door to hybrid treatment strategies that exploit the placebo effect to make real drugs safer and more effective. As Potter says, “To really do the best for your patients, you want the best placebo response plus the best drug response.”",
      "question_count": 3,
      "yes_no_question": {
        "title": "Do the following statements agree with the claims of the writer?",
        "priority": 1,
        "questions": [
          {
            "question": "Merck's experience with MK-869 was unique.",
            "answer": "NO",
            "answer_description": "MK-869 has not been the only much-awaited medical breakthrough to be undone in recent years by the placebo effect."
          },
          {
            "question": "These days, a small number of unsuccessful test results can ruin a well-established drugs company.",
            "answer": "YES",
            "answer_description": "In today's economy, the fate of a well-established company can hang on the outcome of a handful of tests."
          },
          {
            "question": "Some medical conditions are more easily treated by a placebo than others.",
            "answer": "NOT GIVEN",
            "answer_description": "Medical conditions are mentioned, but there is nothing about their relative response to a placebo."
          },
          {
            "question": "It was to be expected that the third group in Kaptchuk’s trial would do better than the other two groups.",
            "answer": "YES",
            "answer_description": "Not surprisingly, the health of those in the third group improved most."
          },
          {
            "question": "Kaptchuk’s research highlights the fact that combined drug and placebo treatments should be avoided.",
            "answer": "NO",
            "answer_description": "Studies like this open the door to hybrid treatment Strategies that exploit the placebo effect to make real drugs safer and more effective. As Potter says, “To really do the best for your patients, you want the best placebo response plus the best drug response.”"
          }
        ]
      },
      "matching_question": {
        "title": "Complete the summary using the list of wards below.\n\nMerck and MK-869",
        "choices": [
          "activity",
          "prices",
          "success",
          "patient",
          "tests",
          "diseases",
          "symptoms",
          "competition",
          "criticism"
        ],
        "priority": 2,
        "questions": [
          {
            "question": "As a result of concerns about increasing $...$ in the drugs industry, the pharmaceutical company Merck decided to Increase its $...$ in the anti-depressant market. The development of the drug MK-869 was seen as the way forward. Initially, MK-869 had some $...$ , but later trials revealed a different picture. Although key $...$ could be treated with the drug, a sugar pill was proving equally effective. In the end, the $...$ indicated that it was pointless continuing with the development of the drug.",
            "answers": [
              {
                "answer": "competition",
                "answer_description": "... Merck, a global pharmaceutical company, was failing behind its rivals in sales. To make matters worse, patents on five blockbuster drugs were about to expire, which would allow cheaper generic products to flood the market."
              },
              {
                "answer": "activity",
                "answer_description": "Key to his strategy was expanding the company's reach into the ant-depressant market ..."
              },
              {
                "answer": "success",
                "answer_description": "The drug tested extremely well early on ..."
              },
              {
                "answer": "symptoms",
                "answer_description": "True, many test subjects treated with the medication felt their hopelessness and anxiety lift."
              },
              {
                "answer": "tests",
                "answer_description": "Ultimately, Merck's venture into the anti-depressant market failed. In the jargon of the industry, the trials crossed the “futility boundary”"
              }
            ]
          }
        ]
      },
      "single_choice_question": {
        "title": "Choose the correct letter, A, B, C or D",
        "priority": 3,
        "questions": [
          {
            "question": "Which of the following is true of William Potter's research?",
            "choices": [
              "It was based on recently developed drugs that he had recommended.",
              "It included trial results from a range of drugs companies.",
              "Some of the trial results he investigated had not been made public.",
              "Some of his findings were not accepted by the drugs industry."
            ],
            "answer": "C",
            "description": "... Potter combed through his company's database of published and unpublished trials—including those that had been kept secret because of high placebo response."
          },
          {
            "question": "What did William Potter's research reveal about the location of drugs trials?",
            "choices": [
              "The placebo effect was weakest in the US.",
              "Results were not consistent around the world.",
              "Results varied depending on the type of hospital.",
              "The FDA preferred drugs to be tested in different countries,"
            ],
            "answer": "B",
            "description": "Potter discovered, however, that geographic location alone could determine the outcome."
          },
          {
            "question": "hat does the tight race refer to in line 80?",
            "choices": [
              "the standard tests",
              "consistent results",
              "ratings by trial observers",
              "testing sites"
            ],
            "answer": "A",
            "description": "Judges are being compared to trial observers, and both assess the results of something. In the case of judges, it is who crossed the finish line first in a race. In the case of trial observers, it is the level of improvement among volunteers in standard tests. A tight race is one where the participants finish very close together, making it hard to say who has won."
          },
          {
            "question": "What significant discovery was made by Ted Kaptchuk?",
            "choices": [
              "The effects of a placebo can last longer than previously thought.",
              "Patients’ health can improve while waiting to undergo a trial.",
              "Patients respond better to a placebo if they are treated by the same clinician throughout the trial.",
              "Those conducting a placebo trial need to know the subjects’ disorder well."
            ],
            "answer": "A",
            "description": "And the benefits of their “bogus” treatment persisted for weeks afterward, contrary to the belief—widespread in the pharmaceutical industry—that the placebo response is short-lived."
          }
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "reading_title": "The history of the poster",
      "reading_content": "The first posters were known as 'broadsides' and were used for public and commercial announcements. Printed on one side only using metal type, they were quickly and crudely produced in large quantities. As they were meant to be read at a distance, they required large lettering.\nThere were a number of negative aspects of large metal type. It was expensive, required a large amount of storage space, and was extremely heavy. If a printer did have a collection of large metal type, it was likely that there were not enough letters, So printers did their best by mixing and matching styles.\nCommercial pressure for the large type was answered with the invention of a system for wood-type production. In 1827, Darius Wells invented a special wood drill - the lateral router - capable of cutting letters on wood blacks, The router was used in combination with William Leavenworth's pantograph (1834) to create decorative wooden letters of all shapes and sizes, The first posters began to appear, but they had little colour and design; often wooden type was mixed with metal type in a conglomeration of styles.\nA major development in poster design was the application of lithography, invented by Alois Senefelder in 1796, which allowed artists to hand-draw letters, opening the field of type design to endless styles. The method involved drawing with a greasy crayon onto finely surfaced Bavarian limestone and offsetting that image onto paper, This direct process captured the artist's true intention: however, the final printed image was In reverse. The images and lettering needed to be drawn backwards often reflected in a mirror or traced on transfer paper. \nAs a result of this technical difficulty, the invention of the lithographic process had little impact on posters until the 1880s, when Jules Cheret came up with his 'three-stone lithographic process'. This gave artists the opportunity to experiment with a wide spectrum of colours. Although the process was difficult, the result was remarkable, with nuances of colour impossible in other media even to this day. The ability to mix words and images in such an attractive and economical format finally made the lithographic poster a powerful innovation.\nStarting in the 1870s, posters became the main vehicle for advertising prior to the magazine era and the dominant means of mass communication in the rapidly growing cities of Europe and America, Yet in the streets of Paris, Milan and Berlin, these artistic prints were so popular that they were stolen off walls almost as soon as they were hung. Cheret, later known as 'the father of the modern poster', organised the first exhibition of posters In 1884 and two years later published the first book on poster art. He quickly took advantage of the public interest by arranging for artists to create posters, at a reduced size, that were suitable for in-home display.\nThanks to Cheret. the poster slowly took hold in other countries in the 1890s and came to celebrate each society's unique cultural institutions: the café in France, the opera and fashion in Italy, festivals in Spain, literature in Holland, and trade fairs in Germany. The first poster shows were held in Great Britain and Italy in 1894, Germany in 1896, and Russia in 1897. The most important poster show ever, to many observers, was held in Reims, France. in 1896 and featured an unbelievable 1.690 posters arranged by country.\nIn the early 20th century, the poster continued to play a large communication role and to go through a range of styles. By the 1950s, however, it had begun to share the spotlight with other media, mainly radio and print. By this time, most posters were printed using the mass production technique of photo offset, which resulted in the familiar dot pattern seen in newspapers and magazines. In addition, the use of photography in posters, begun in Russia in the twenties, started to become as common as illustration. \nIn the late fifties, a new graphic style that had a strong reliance on typographic elements in black and white appeared. The new style came to be known as the International Typographic Style. it made use of a mathematical grid, strict graphic rules, and black-and-white photography to provide a clear and logical structure. It became the predominant style in the world in the 1970s and continues to exert its influence today.\nIt was perfectly suited to the increasingly international post-war marketplace, where there was a strong demand for clarity. This meant that the accessibility of words and symbols had to be taken into account. Corporations wanted international identification, and events such as the Olympics called for universal solutions, which the Typographic Style could provide.\nHowever, the International Typographic Style began to lose its energy in the late 1970s. Many criticised It for being cold, formal, and dogmatic. A young teacher in Basel, Wolfgang Weingart, experimented with the offset printing process to produce posters that appeared complex and chaotic, playful and spontaneous - all in stark contrast to what had gone before, Weingart's liberation of typography was an important foundation for several new styles. These ranged from Memphis and Retro to the advances now being made in computer graphics.",
      "question_count": 2,
      "gap_question": {
        "title": "Complete the table below.\nChoose NO MORE THAN THREE WORDS from the passage for each answer.\nEarly Printing Methods",
        "priority": 1,
        "questions": [
          {
            "question": " \n ⚪ Metal type features: \n  - produced large print \n ⚫ Metal type problems: \n - cost, weight and $...$ difficulties \n - mixed styles",
            "answers": [
              {
                "answer": [
                  "storage",
                  "storage space"
                ]
              }
            ]
          },
          {
            "question": " \n ⚪ Wood type features: \n - Darius's wood drill used in connection with another $...$ \n - produced a range of letters \n ⚫ Wood type problems: \n - lacked both $...$ \n - mixed type",
            "answers": [
              {
                "answer": [
                  "invention"
                ]
              },
              {
                "answer": [
                  "colour and design",
                  "design and colour",
                  "color and design",
                  "design and color"
                ],
                "answer_description": "_color_ for American spelling and _colour_ for British spelling"
              }
            ]
          },
          {
            "question": " \n ⚪ Lithography features: \n - letters drawn by hands \n - design tool a $...$ \n ⚫ Lithography problems: \n - had to use a mirror or $...$ to achieve correct image",
            "answers": [
              {
                "answer": [
                  "crayon",
                  "greasy crayon"
                ]
              },
              {
                "answer": [
                  "transfer paper"
                ]
              }
            ]
          }
        ]
      },
      "true_false_question": {
        "title": "Read the passage and decide whether each question is TRUE, FALSE or NOT GIVEN",
        "priority": 2,
        "questions": [
          {
            "question": "By the 1950s, photographs were more widely seen than artists’ illustrations on posters.",
            "answer": "FALSE",
            "answer_description": "By this time, ... the use of photography in posters, begun in Russia in the twenties, started to become as common as illustration."
          },
          {
            "question": "Features of the Typographic Style can be seen in modern-day posters.",
            "answer": "TRUE",
            "answer_description": "It became the predominant style in the world in the 1970s and continues to exert its Influence today."
          },
          {
            "question": "The Typographic Style met a global need at a particular time in history.",
            "answer": "TRUE",
            "answer_description": "It was perfectly suited to the increasingly international post-war marketplace, where there was a strong demand for clarity."
          },
          {
            "question": "Weingart got many of his ideas from his students in Basel.",
            "answer": "NOT GIVEN",
            "answer_description": "Weingart is mentioned, but nothing is said about where his ideas originated."
          }
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "reading_title": "Last man standing",
      "reading_content": "Some 50,000 years ago, Homo sapiens beat other hominids to become the only surviving species. Kate Ravilious reveals how we did it.\nToday, there are over seven billion people living on Earth. No other species has exerted as much influence over the planet as us. But turn the clock back 80,000 years and we were one of a number of species roaming the Earth. Our species, Homo sapiens [Latin for ‘wise man’], was most successful in Africa. In western Eurasia, the Neanderthals dominated, while Homo erectus may have lived in Indonesia. Meanwhile, an unusual finger bone and tooth, discovered in Denisova cave in Siberia In 2008, have led scientists to believe that yet another human population - the Denisovans - may also have been widespread across Asia. Somewhere along the line, these other human species died out, leaving Home sapiens as the sole survivor. So what made us the winners in the battle for survival?\n\nSome 74,000 years ago, the Toba ‘supervolcano’ on the Indonesian island of Sumatra erupted. The scale of the event was so great that ash from the eruption was flung as far as eastern India, more than 2,000 kilometres away Oxford archaeologist Mike Petraglia and his team have uncovered thousands of stone tools buried underneath the Toba ash. The mix of hand axes and spear tips has led Petraglia to speculate that Homo sapiens and Homo erectus were both living in eastern India prior to the Toba eruption. Based on careful examination of the tools and dating of the sediment layers where they were found. Petraglia and his team suggest that Homo sapiens arrived in eastern India around 78,000 years ago, migrating out of Africa and across Arabia during a favourable climate period. After their arrival, the simple tools belonging to Homo erectus seemed to lessen in number and eventually disappear completely. ‘We think that Homo sapiens had a more efficient hunting technology, which could have given them the edge,’ says Petraglia. ‘Whether the eruption of Toba also played a role in the extinction of the Homo erectus-like species is unclear to us.’\n\nSome 45,000 years later, another fight for survival took place. This time, the location was Europe and the protagonists were another species, the Neanderthals. They were a highly successful species that dominated the European landscape for 300,000 years. Yet within just a few thousand years of the arrival of Homo sapiens, their numbers plummeted, They eventually disappeared from the landscape around 30,000 years ago, with their last known refuge being southern Iberia, including Gibraltar. Initially, Homo sapiens and Neanderthals lived alongside each other and had no reason to compete. But then Europe's climate swung into a cold, inhospitable one, dry phase. ‘Neanderthal and Homo sapiens populations had to retreat to refugia [pockets of habitable land]. This heightened competition between the two groups,’ explains Chris Stringer, an anthropologist at the Natural History Museum in London. \n\nBoth species were strong and stockier than the average human today, but Neanderthals were particularly robust. ‘Their skeletons show that they had broad shoulders and thick necks,’ says Stringer. ‘Homo sapiens, on the other hand, had longer forearms, which undoubtedly enabled them to throw a spear from some distance, with less danger and using relatively little energy,’ explains Stringer. This long-range ability may have given Homo sapiens an advantage in hunting. When it came to keeping warm, Homo sapiens had another skill: weaving and sewing. Archaeologists have uncovered simple needles fashioned from ivory and bone alongside Homo sapiens, dating as far back as 35,000 years ago. ‘Using this technology, we could use animal skins to make ourselves tents, warm clothes, and fur boots,’ says Stringer. In contrast, Neanderthals never seemed to master sewing skills, instead relying on pinning skins together with thorns. \n\nA thirst for exploration provided Homo sapiens with another significant advantage over Neanderthals. Objects such as shell beads and flint tools, were discovered many miles from their source, show that our ancestors travelled over large distances, in order to barter and exchange useful materials, and share ideas and knowledge. By contrast, Neanderthals tended to keep themselves to themselves, Living in small groups. They misdirected their energies by only gathering resources from their immediate surroundings and perhaps failing to discover new technologies outside their territory.\n\nSome of these differences in behaviour may have emerged because the two species thought in different ways. By comparing skull shapes, archaeologists have shown that Homo sapiens had a more developed temporal lobe —the regions at the side of the brain, associated with listening, language, and long-term memory. ‘We think that Homo sapiens had a significantly more complex language than Neanderthals and were able to comprehend and discuss concepts such as the distant past and future,’ says Stringer. Penny Spikins, an archaeologist at the University of York, has recently suggested that Homo sapiens may also have had a greater diversity of brain types than Neanderthals. ‘Our research indicates that high-precision tools, new hunting technologies, and the development of symbolic communication may all have come about because they were willing to include people with “different” minds and specialised roles in their society,’ she explains. ‘We see similar kinds of injuries on male and female Neanderthal skeletons, implying there was no such division of labour,’ says Spikins. \n\nThus by around 30,000 years ago, many talents and traits were well established in Homo sapiens societies but still absent from Neanderthal communities. Stringer thinks that the Neanderthals were just living in the wrong place at the wrong time. ‘They had to compete with Homo sapiens during a phase of very unstable climate across Europe. During each rapid climate fluctuation, they may have suffered greater losses of people than Homo sapiens, and thus were slowly worn down,’ he says. ‘if the climate had remained stable throughout, they might still be here.’",
      "question_count": 2,
      "gap_question": {
        "title": "Complete the sentences below. Choose NO MORE THAN THREE WORDS from the passage for each answer.",
        "priority": 1,
        "questions": [
          {
            "question": "Analysis of stone tools and $...$ has enabled Petraglia's team to put forward an arrival date for Homo sapiens in eastern India.",
            "answers": [
              {
                "answer": [
                  "sediment layers",
                  "dating sediment layers"
                ],
                "answer_description": "Based on careful examination of the tools and dating of the sediment layers where they were found, Petraglia and his team suggest that Homo sapiens arrived in eastern India around 78,000 years age ..."
              }
            ]
          },
          {
            "question": "Homo sapiens used both $...$ to make sewing implements.",
            "answers": [
              {
                "answer": [
                  "ivory and bone",
                  "bone and ivory"
                ],
                "answer_description": "Archaeologists have uncovered simple needles fashioned from ivory and bone, alongside Homo sapiens ..."
              }
            ]
          },
          {
            "question": "The territorial nature of Neanderthals may have limited their ability to acquire resources and $...$ .",
            "answers": [
              {
                "answer": [
                  "technologies",
                  "new technologies"
                ],
                "answer_description": "They misdirected their energies by only gathering resources from their immediate surroundings and perhaps failing to discover new technologies outside their territory."
              }
            ]
          },
          {
            "question": "Archaeologists examined $...$ in order to get an insight into Neanderthal and Homo sapiens’ capacity for language and thought.",
            "answers": [
              {
                "answer": [
                  "skull shapes"
                ],
                "answer_description": "By comparing skull shapes ..."
              }
            ]
          }
        ]
      },
      "matching_question": {
        "title": "Look at the following statements and the list of researchers.\nMatch each statement with the correct researcher.",
        "choices": [
          "Mike Petraglia",
          "Chris Stringer",
          "Penny Spikins"
        ],
        "priority": 2,
        "questions": [
          {
            "question": "No evidence can be found to suggest that Neanderthal communities allocated tasks to different members. \n ⭕ $...$",
            "answers": [
              {
                "answer": "Penny Spikins",
                "answer_description": "‘We see similar kinds of injuries on male and female Neanderthal skeletons, implying there was no such division of labour,’ says Spikins."
              }
            ]
          },
          {
            "question": "Homo sapiens may have been able to plan ahead. \n ⭕ $...$",
            "answers": [
              {
                "answer": "Chris Stringer",
                "answer_description": "‘We think that Homo sapiens had a significantly more complex language than Neanderthals and were able to comprehend and discuss concepts such as the distant past and future,’ says Stringer."
              }
            ]
          },
          {
            "question": "Scientists cannot be sure whether a sudden natural disaster contributed to the loss of a human species. \n ⭕ $...$",
            "answers": [
              {
                "answer": "Mike Petraglia",
                "answer_description": "... says Petraglia. ‘Whether the eruption of Toba also played a role in the extinction of the Homo erectus-like species is unclear to us.’"
              }
            ]
          }
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "reading_title": "The new way to be fifth-grader",
      "reading_content": "I peer over his shoulder at his laptop screen to see the math problem the fifth-grader is pondering. It's a trigonometry problem. Carpenter, a serious-faced ten-year-old, pauses for a second, fidgets, then clicks on “0 degrees.” The computer tells him that he's correct. “It took a while for me to work it out,” he admits sheepishly. The software then generates another problem, followed by another, until eventually, hers done ten in a row.\nLast November, his teacher, Kami Thordarson, began using Khan Academy in her class. It is an educational website on which students can watch some 2,400 videos. The videos are anything but sophisticated. At seven to 14 minutes long, they consist of a voiceover by the site's founder, Salman Khan, chattily describing a mathematical concept or explaining how to solve a problem, while his hand-scribbled formulas and diagrams appear on-screen. As a student, you can review a video as many times as you want, scrolling back several times over puzzling parts and fast-forwarding through the boring bits you already know. Once you've mastered a video, you can move on to the next one.\nInitially, Thordarson thought Khan Academy would merely be a helpful supplement to her normal instruction. But it quickly became far more than that. She is now on her way to “flipping” the way her class works. This involves replacing some: of her lectures with Khan's videos, which students can watch at home. Then in class, they focus on working on the problem areas together. The idea is to invert the normal rhythms of school, so that lectures are viewed in the children's own time and homework is done at school. It sounds weird, Thordarson admits, but this reversal makes sense when you think about it. It is when they are doing homework that students are really grappling with a subject and are most likely to want someone to talk to. And Khan Academy provides teachers with a dashboard application that lets them see the instant a student gets stuck.\nFor years, teachers like Thordarson have complained about the frustrations of teaching to the “middle” of the class. They stand at the whiteboard trying to get 25 or more students to learn at the same pace. Advanced students get bored and tune out, lagging ones get lost and tune out, and pretty soon half the class is not paying attention. Since the rise of personal computers in the 1980s, educators have hoped that technology could save the day by offering lessons tailored to each child. Schools have spent millions of dollars on sophisticated classroom technology, but the effort has been in vain, The one-to-one instruction it requires is, after all, prohibitively expensive. What country can afford such a luxury?\nKhan never intended to overhaul the school curricula and he doesn't have a consistent, comprehensive plan for doing so. Nevertheless, some of his fans believe that he has stumbled onto the solution to education's middle-of-the-class mediocrity. Most notable among them Is Bill Gates, whose foundation has Invested $1.5 million in khan's site. Students have pointed out that Khan is particularly good at explaining all the hidden, small steps in math problems—steps that teachers often gloss over. He has an uncanny ability to inhabit the mind of someone who doesn't already understand something.\nHowever, not all educators are enamoured with Khan and his site. Gary Stager, a long-time educational consultant, and advocate of laptops in classrooms thinks Khan Academy is not innovative at all, The videos and software modules, he contends, are just a high-tech version of the outdated teaching techniques—lecturing and drilling. Schools have become “joyless test-prep factories,” he says, and Khan Academy caters to this dismal trend.\nAs Sylvia Martinez, president of an organization focusing on technology in the classroom, puts it, “The things they're doing are really just rote.” Flipping the classroom isn't an entirely new idea, Martinez says, and she doubts that it would work for the majority of pupils: “I'm sorry, but if they can't understand the lecture in a classroom, they're not going to grasp It better when it's done through a video at home.”\nAnother limitation of Khan's site is that the drilling software can only handle questions where the answers are unambiguously right or wrong, like math or chemistry; Khan has relatively few videos on messier, grey-area subjects like history. Khan and Gates admit there is no easy way to automate the teaching of writing—even though it is just as critical as math.\nEven if Khan is truly liberating students to advance at their own pace, it is not clear that schools will be able to cope. The very concept of grade levels Implies groups of students moving along together at an even pace. So what happens when, using Khan Academy, you wind up with a ten-year-old who has already mastered high-school physics? Khan's programmer, Ben Kamens, has heard from teachers who have seen Khan Academy presentations and loved the Idea but wondered whether they could modify it “to stop students from becoming this advanced.”\nKhan's success has injected him into the heated wars over school reform. Reformers today, by and large, believe student success should be carefully tested, with teachers and principals receiving better pay if their students advance more quickly. In essence, Khan doesn't want to change the way institutions teach; he wants to change how people learn, whether they're in a private school or a public school—or for that matter, whether they're a student or an adult trying to self-educate in Ohio, Brazil, Russia, or India. One member of Khan's staff is spearheading a drive to translate the videos into ten major languages. It's classic start-up logic: do something novel, do it with speed, and the people who love it will find you.",
      "question_count": 3,
      "single_choice_question": {
        "title": "Choose the correct letter, A, B, C or D",
        "priority": 1,
        "questions": [
          {
            "question": "What do you learn about the student in the first paragraph?",
            "choices": [
              "He has not used the maths software before.",
              "He did not expect his answer to the problem to be correct.",
              "He was not initially doing the right maths problem.",
              "He did not immediately know how to solve the maths problem."
            ],
            "answer": "D",
            "description": "“It took a while for me to work it out,” ..."
          },
          {
            "question": "What does the writer say about the content of the Khan Academy videos?",
            "choices": [
              "They have been produced in a professional manner.",
              "They include a mix of verbal and visual features.",
              "Some of the maths problems are too easy.",
              "Some of the explanations are too brief."
            ],
            "answer": "B",
            "description": "... they consist of a voiceover by the site's founder, Salman Khan, chattily describing a mathematical concept or explaining how to solve a problem, while his hand-scribbled formulas and diagrams appear on-screen."
          },
          {
            "question": "What does this reversal refer to in line 40?",
            "choices": [
              "going back to spending fewer hours in school",
              "students being asked to explain answers to teachers",
              "swapping the activities done in the class and at home",
              "the sudden improvement in students’ maths performance"
            ],
            "answer": "C",
            "description": "This involves replacing some of her lectures with Khan's videos, which students can watch at home."
          },
          {
            "question": "What does the writer say about teaching to the middle of the class?",
            "choices": [
              "Teachers become too concerned about weaker students.",
              "Technology has not until now provided a solution to the problem.",
              "Educators have been unwilling to deal with the issues.",
              "Students in this category quickly become bored."
            ],
            "answer": "B",
            "description": "Schools have spent millions of dollars on sophisticated classroom technology, but the effort has been in vain."
          },
          {
            "question": "Students praise Khan's videos because they",
            "choices": [
              "show the extent of his mathematical knowledge.",
              "deal with a huge range of maths problems.",
              "provide teaching at different ability levels.",
              "cover details that are often omitted in class."
            ],
            "answer": "D",
            "description": "... steps that teachers often gloss over."
          }
        ]
      },
      "yes_no_question": {
        "title": "Do the following statements agree with the claims of the writer in the reading passage?",
        "priority": 2,
        "questions": [
          {
            "question": "Thordarson’s first impressions of how she would use Khan Academy turned out to be wrong.",
            "answer": "YES",
            "answer_description": "Initially, Thordarson thought Khan Academy would merely be a helpful supplement to her normal instruction. But it quickly became far more than that."
          },
          {
            "question": "Khan wished to completely change the way courses are taught in schools.",
            "answer": "NO",
            "answer_description": "Khan never intended to overhaul the school curricula and he doesn’t have a consistent, comprehensive plan for doing so."
          },
          {
            "question": "School grade levels are based on the idea of students progressing at different rates.",
            "answer": "NO",
            "answer_description": "The very concept of grade levels implies groups of students moving along together at an even pace."
          },
          {
            "question": "Some principals have invited Khan into their schools to address students.",
            "answer": "NOT GIVEN",
            "answer_description": "Principals are mentioned, but there is nothing about them inviting Khan into their schools."
          },
          {
            "question": "Khan has given advice to other people involved in start-up projects.",
            "answer": "NOT GIVEN",
            "answer_description": "Start-ups are mentioned, but there is nothing about Khan giving advice on them."
          }
        ]
      },
      "matching_question": {
        "title": "Complete each sentence with the correct ending, below.",
        "choices": [
          "is only suited to subjects where questions have exact answers.",
          "can teach both the strongest and the weakest pupils in a class.",
          "means the teaching of other school subjects will have to be changed.",
          "only prepares students to pass exams.",
          "could cause student achievement to improve too quickly.",
          "requires all students to own the necessary technology.",
          "is unlikely to have a successful outcome most students."
        ],
        "priority": 3,
        "questions": [
          {
            "question": "Bill Gates thinks Khan Academy $...$",
            "answers": [
              {
                "answer": "can teach both the strongest and the weakest pupils in a class.",
                "answer_description": "Nevertheless, some of his fans believe that he has stumbled onto the solution to education’s middle-of-the-class mediocrity, Most notable among them is Bill Gates, ..."
              }
            ]
          },
          {
            "question": "According to Gary Stager, Khan Academy $...$",
            "answers": [
              {
                "answer": "only prepares students to pass exams.",
                "answer_description": "Schools have become “joyless test-prep factories,” he says, and Khan Academy caters to this dismal trend."
              }
            ]
          },
          {
            "question": "Sylvia Martinez regrets that Khan Academy $...$",
            "answers": [
              {
                "answer": "is unlikely to have a successful outcome most students.",
                "answer_description": "... she doubts that it would work for the majority of pupils ..."
              }
            ]
          },
          {
            "question": "Ben Kamens has been told that Khan Academy $...$",
            "answers": [
              {
                "answer": "could cause student achievement to improve too quickly.",
                "answer_description": "... wondered whether they could modify it “to stop students from becoming this advanced.”"
              }
            ]
          }
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "reading_title": "Gold dusters",
      "reading_content": "Row upon row, tomato plants stand in formation inside a greenhouse. To reproduce, most flowering plants depend on a third party to transfer pollen between their male and female parts. Some require extra encouragement to give up that golden dust. The tomato flower, for example, needs a violent shake, a vibration roughly equivalent to 30 times the pull of Earth's gravity, explains Arizona entomologist Stephen Buchmann. Growers have tried numerous ways to rattle pollen from tomato blossoms. They have used shaking tables, air blowers, and blasts of sound. But natural means seem to work better.\n\nIt is no surprise that nature's design works best. What's astonishing is the array of workers that do it more than 200,000 individual animal species, by varying strategies, help the world's 240,000 species of flowering plants make more flowers. Flies and beetles are the original pollinators, going back to when \nflowering plants first appeared 130 million years ago. As for bees, scientists have identified some 20,000 distinct species so far. Hummingbirds, butterflies, moths, wasps, and ants are also up to the job. Even non-flying mammals do their part, sugar-loving opossums, some rainforest monkeys, and lemurs in Madagascar, all with nimble hands that tear open flower stalks and furry coats to which pollen sticks. Most surprisingly, some lizards, such as geckos, lap up nectar and pollen and then transport the stuff on their faces and feet as they forage onward.\n\nAll that messy diversity, unfortunately, is not well suited to the monocrops and mega-yields of modern commercial farmers. Before farms got so big, says conservation biologist Claire Kremen of the University of California, Berkeley, ‘we didn't have to manage pollinators. They were all around because of the diverse landscapes. Now you need to bring in an army to get pollination done,’ The European honeybee was first imported to the US some 400 years ago. Now at least a hundred commercial crops rely almost entirely on managed honeybees, which beekeepers raise and rent out to tend to big farms. And although other species of bees are five to ten times more efficient, on a per-bee basis, at pollinating certain fruits, honeybees have bigger colonies, cover longer distances, and tolerate management and movement better than most insects. They're not picky - they'll spend their time on almost any crop. It's tricky to calculate what their work is truly worth; some economists put it at more than $200 billion globally a year.\n\nIndustrial-scale farming, however, may be wearing down the system. Honeybees have suffered diseases and parasite infestations for as long as they've been managed, but in 2006 came an extreme blow. Around the world, bees began to disappear over the winter in massive numbers. Beekeepers would lift the lid of a hive and be amazed to find only the queen and a few stragglers, the worker bees gone. In the US, a third to half of all hives crashed; some beekeepers reported colony losses near 90 percent. The mysterious culprit was named colony collapse disorder (CCD) and it remains an annual menace -and an enigma.\n\nWhen it first hit, many people, from agronomists to the public, assumed that our slathering of chemicals on agricultural fields was to blame for the mystery. Indeed, says Jeff Pettis of the USDA Bee Research Laboratory, ‘we do find more disease in bees that have been exposed to pesticides, even at low levels.’ But it is likely that CCD involves multiple stressors. Poor nutrition and chemical exposure, for instance, might wear down a bee's immunities before a virus finishes the insect off. It's hard to tease apart factors and outcomes, Pettis says. New studies reveal that fungicides - not previously thought toxic to bees - can interfere with microbes that break down pollen in the insects' guts, affecting nutrient absorption and thus long-term health and longevity. Some findings pointed to viral and fungal pathogens working together. ‘I only wish we had a single agent causing all the declines,’ Pettis says, ‘that would make our work much easier.’\n\nHowever, habitat loss and alteration, he says, are even more of a menace to pollinators than pathogens. Claire Kremen encourages farmers to cultivate the flora surrounding farmland to help solve habitat problems. ‘You can't move the farm,’ she says, ‘but you can diversify what grows in its vicinity: along roads, even in tractor yards.’ Planting hedgerows and patches of native flowers that bloom at different times and seeding fields with multiple plant species rather than monocrops ‘not only is better for native pollinators, but its just better agriculture,’ she says. Pesticide-free wildflower havens, adds Buchmann, would also bolster populations of useful insects. Fortunately, too, ‘there are far more generalist plants than specialist plants, so there's a lot of redundancy in pollination,’ Buchmann says. ‘Even if one pollinator drops out, there are often pretty good surrogates left to do the job.’ The key to keeping our gardens growing strong, he says, is letting that diversity thrive.\n\nTake away that variety, and we'll lose more than honey. ‘We wouldn't starve,’ says Kremen, But what we eat, and even what we wear — pollinators, after all, give us some of our cotton and flax — would be limited to crops whose pollen travels by other means. ‘In a sense,’ she says, ‘our lives would be dictated by the wind.’ It's vital that we give pollinators more of what they need and less of what they don't, and ease the burden on managed bees by letting native animals do their part, say scientists.",
      "question_count": 2,
      "gap_question": {
        "title": "Complete the sentences below. Choose NO MORE THAN THREE WORDS from the passage for each answer.",
        "priority": 1,
        "questions": [
          {
            "question": "Both $...$ were the first creatures to pollinate the world's plants.",
            "answers": [
              {
                "answer": [
                  "flies and beetles"
                ]
              }
            ]
          },
          {
            "question": "Monkeys transport pollen on their $...$ .",
            "answers": [
              {
                "answer": [
                  "coats",
                  "furry coats"
                ]
              }
            ]
          },
          {
            "question": "Honeybees are favoured pollinators among bee species partly because they travel $...$ .",
            "answers": [
              {
                "answer": [
                  "distances",
                  "longer distances"
                ]
              }
            ]
          },
          {
            "question": "A feature of CCD is often the loss of all the $...$ .",
            "answers": [
              {
                "answer": [
                  "worker bees"
                ]
              }
            ]
          }
        ]
      },
      "multi_choice_question": {
        "title": "Choose TWO letter, A-E",
        "priority": 2,
        "questions": [
          {
            "question": "Which TWO methods of combating the problems caused by CCD and habitat loss are mentioned in the article?",
            "selection_count": 2,
            "choices": [
              "using more imported pest controllers",
              "removing microbes from bees’ stomachs",
              "cultivating a wide range of flowering plants",
              "increasing the size of many farms",
              "placing less reliance on honeybees"
            ],
            "answers": [
              {
                "answer": "C",
                "description": "Claire Kremen encourages farmers ... useful insects."
              },
              {
                "answer": "E",
                "description": "it's vital that we ... ease the burden on managed bees by letting native animals do their part ..."
              }
            ]
          }
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "reading_title": "The Earth and Space Foundation",
      "reading_content": "<bold>Inches</bold> The community that focuses its efforts on the exploration of space has largely been different from the community focused on the study and protection of the Earth's environment, despite the fact that both fields of interest involve what might be referred to as ‘scientific exploration’. The reason for this dichotomous \nexistence is chiefly historical. The exploration of the Earth has been occurring over many centuries, and the institutions created to do it are often very different from those founded in the second part of the 20th century to explore space. This separation is also caused by the fact that space exploration has attracted experts from mainly non-biological disciplines — primarily engineers and physicists — but the study of Earth and its environment is a domain heavily populated by biologists.\n\nThe separation between the two communities is often reflected in attitudes. In the environmental community, it is not uncommon for space exploration to be regarded as a waste of money, distracting governments from solving major environmental problems here at home. In the space exploration community, it is not uncommon for environmentalists to be regarded as introspective people who divert attention from the more expansive visions of the exploration of space — the ‘new frontier’. These perceptions can also be negative in consequence because the full potential of both communities can be realised better when they work together to solve problems. For example, those involved in space exploration can provide the satellites to monitor the Earth's fragile environments, and environmentalists can provide information on the survival of life in extreme environments. \n\nIn the sense that Earth and space exploration both stem from the same human drive to understand our environment and our place within it, there is no reason for the split to exist. A more accurate view of Earth and space exploration is to see them as a continuum of exploration with many interconnected and mutually beneficial links. The Earth and Space Foundation, a registered charity, was established for the purpose of fostering such links through field research and by direct practical action.\n\nProjects that have been supported by the Foundation include environmental projects using technologies resulting from space exploration, satellite communications, GPS, remote sensing, advanced materials, and power sources. For example, in places where people are faced with the destruction of the forests on which their livelihood depends, rather than rejecting economic progress and trying to save the forests on their intrinsic merit, another approach is to enhance the value of the forests — although these schemes must be carefully assessed to be successful. In the past, the Foundation provided a grant to a group of expeditions that used remote sensing to plan eco-tourism routes in the forests of Guatemala, thus providing capital to the local communities through the tourist trade. This novel approach is now making the protection of the forests a sensible economic decision.\n\nThe Foundation funds expeditions making astronomical observations from remote, difficult-to-access Earth locations, archaeological field projects studying the development of early civilisations that made significant contributions to astronomy and space sciences, and field expeditions studying the way in which views of the astronomical environment shaped the nature of past civilisations. A part of Syria — ‘the Fertile Crescent’ — was the birthplace of astronomy, accountancy, animal domestication, and many other fundamental developments of human civilisation. The Foundation helped fund a large archaeology project by the Society for Syrian Archaeology at the University of California, Los Angeles, in collaboration with the Syrian government that used GPS and satellite imagery to locate mounds, or ‘tels’ , containing artefacts and remnants of early civilisations. These collections are being used to build a better picture of the nature of the civilisations that gave birth to astronomy.\n\nField research also applies the Earth's environmental and biological resources to the human exploration and settlement of space. This may include the use of remote environments on Earth, as well as physiological and psychological studies in harsh environments.ln one research project, the Foundation provided a grant to an international caving expedition to study the psychology of explorers subjected to long-term isolation in caves in Mexico. The psychometric tests on the covers were used to enhance US astronaut selection criteria by the NASA Johnson Space Center.\n\nSpace-like environments on Earth help us understand how to operate in the space environment or help us characterise extraterrestrial environments for future scientific research. In the Arctic, a 24-kilometre-wide impact crater formed by an asteroid or comet 23 million years ago has become home to a Mars-analogue programme. The Foundation helped fund the NASA Haughton-Mars Project to use this crater to test communications and exploration technologies in preparation for the human exploration of Mars. The crater, which sits in high Arctic permafrost, provides an excellent replica of the physical processes occurring on Mars, a permafrost, impact-altered planet. Geologists and biologists can work at the site to help understand how impact craters shape the geological characteristics and possibly biological potential of Mars.\n\nIn addition to its fieldwork and scientific activities, the Foundation has award programmes. These include a series of awards for the future human exploration of Mars, a location with a diverse set of exploration challenges. The awards will honour a number of ‘firsts’ on Mars that include landing on the surface, undertaking an overland expedition to the Martian South Pole, undertaking an overland expedition to the Martian North Pole, climbing Olympus Mons, the highest mountain in the solar system, and descending to the bottom of Valles Marineris, the deepest canyon on Mars. The Foundation will offer awards for expeditions further out in the solar system once these Mars awards have been claimed. Together, they demonstrate that the programme really has no boundary in what it could eventually support, and they provide longevity for the objectives of the Foundation.",
      "question_count": 3,
      "yes_no_question": {
        "title": "Do the following statements agree with the views of the writer in the reading passage?",
        "priority": 1,
        "questions": [
          {
            "question": "Activities related to environmental protection and space exploration have a common theme.",
            "answer": "YES",
            "answer_description": "... despite the fact that both fields of interest involve what might be referred to as ‘scientific exploration’"
          },
          {
            "question": "It is unclear why space exploration evolved in a different way from environmental studies on Earth.",
            "answer": "NO",
            "answer_description": "The reason for this dichotomous existence is chiefly historical, The exploration of the Earth has been occurring over many centuries, and the institutions created to do it are often very different from those founded in the second part of the 20th century to explore space, This separation is also caused by the fact that space exploration has attracted experts from mainly non-biological disciplines - primarily engineers and physicists - but the study of Earth and its environment is a domain heavily populated by biologists."
          },
          {
            "question": "Governments tend to allocate more money to environmental projects than space exploration,",
            "answer": "NOT GIVEN",
            "answer_description": "The text mentions governments and money, but nothing is said about how much they allocate to each type of research."
          },
          {
            "question": "Unfortunately, the environmental and space exploration communities have little to offer each other in terms of resources.",
            "answer": "NO",
            "answer_description": "... those involved in space exploration can provide the satellites to monitor the Earth's fragile environments, and environmentalists can provide information on the survival of life in extreme environments."
          },
          {
            "question": "The Earth and Space Foundation was set up later than it was originally intended.",
            "answer": "NOT GIVEN",
            "answer_description": "The Foundation is mentioned, but there is nothing about the timing of its establishment."
          }
        ]
      },
      "single_choice_question": {
        "title": "Choose the correct letter, A, B, C or D",
        "priority": 2,
        "questions": [
          {
            "question": "What was the significance of the ‘novel approach’ adopted in the Guatemala project?",
            "choices": [
              "It minimised the need to protect the forests.",
              "It reduced the impact of tourists on the forests.",
              "It showed that preserving the forests can be profitable.",
              "It gave the Foundation greater control over the forests."
            ],
            "answer": "C",
            "description": "... another approach is to enhance the value of the forests ... This novel approach is now making the protection of the forests a sensible economic decision."
          },
          {
            "question": "GPS and satellite imagery were used in the syrian project to",
            "choices": [
              "help archaeologists find ancient items.",
              "explore land that is hard to reach.",
              "reduce the impact of archaeological activity.",
              "evaluate some early astronomical theories."
            ],
            "answer": "A",
            "description": "... to locate mounds, or ‘tels’, containing artefacts and remnants of early civilisations. These collections are being used to build a better picture of the nature of the civilisations that gave birth to astronomy."
          },
          {
            "question": "One of the purposes of the Foundation's awards is to",
            "choices": [
              "attract non-scientists to its work.",
              "establish priorities for Mars exploration.",
              "offer financial incentives for space exploration.",
              "establish the long-term continuity of its activities."
            ],
            "answer": "D",
            "description": "... they provide longevity far the objectives af the Foundation."
          },
          {
            "question": "What is the writer's purpose in the passage?",
            "choices": [
              "to persuade people to support the Foundation",
              "to explain the nature of the Foundation’s work",
              "to show how views on the Foundation have changed",
              "to reject earlier criticisms of the Foundation’s work"
            ],
            "answer": "B",
            "description": "The writer's tone is explanatory; there are no requests for support, nothing has changed about the Foundation’s work, and there is no reference to any criticisms of the Foundation's work."
          }
        ]
      },
      "matching_question": {
        "title": "Complete the summary using the words, below.",
        "choices": [
          "comparable",
          "extreme",
          "connected",
          "ideal",
          "unexpected",
          "beneficial",
          "scientific",
          "extended",
          "individual"
        ],
        "priority": 3,
        "questions": [
          {
            "question": "Some studies have looked at how humans function in $...$ situations. In one project, it was decided to review cave explorers in Mexico who tolerate $...$ periods on their own.",
            "answers": [
              {
                "answer": "extreme",
                "answer_description": "This may include the use of remote environments on Earth, as well as physiological and psychological studies in harsh environments."
              },
              {
                "answer": "extended",
                "answer_description": "... to study the psychology of explorers subjected to long-term isolation in caves in Mexico."
              }
            ]
          },
          {
            "question": "It is also possible to prepare for space exploration by studying environments on Earth that are $...$ to those on Mars. A huge crater in the Arctic is the $...$ place to test the technologies needed to explore Mars and gather other relevant $...$ information.",
            "answers": [
              {
                "answer": "comparable",
                "answer_description": "Space-like environments on Earth help us understand how to operate in the space environment or help us characterise extraterrestrial environments for future scientific research."
              },
              {
                "answer": "ideal",
                "answer_description": "The crater, which sits in high Arctic permafrost, Provides an excellent replica of the physical processes occurring on Mars ..."
              },
              {
                "answer": "scientific",
                "answer_description": "... and possibly biological potential of Mars."
              }
            ]
          }
        ]
      }
    }
  ]
}
